okay good please remember not to move
no when you're meditating in a group
okay please remember to try not to move
all right okay here we go
and please relax your forehead relax
your mouth corners of your mouth
check your fingers are they tight
stomach in slightly eyelids so
forehead soft and then please come to
your breath long exhales push out the
extra breath
and try to glue your mind to your breath
and try to make sure your mind is
touching your breath as the breath goes
in and out
then I'd like you to check the condition
of your mind
is it pretty smooth I think in the
morning most of us the mind is pretty
calm so check in with your mind how
smooth is it how quiet is the water
and I'd like you to think of a friend
that you have he is a very calm person
good person so in our life we have a few
friends who have a good effect on us
when we spend time with them they're
always doing nice things they treat
other people well they say nice things
to other people they're kind they're
respectful considerate of other people
so I'd like you to go through a list of
your friends and pick out one who could
sit with us today across from us so
instead of our llama instead of our
teacher or parents we are sitting across
from good friend good person
and check in with your the water of your
mind again how smooth is it and you
might also check your heartbeat and your
breathing as the water changed after you
brought your good friend to meditate
with you
then we all have friends who are not so
nice
maybe they criticize people a lot or
don't speak nicely to people maybe
they're a little bit selfish still we
spend time with them so I'd like you to
switch the person meditating with you
and make it one of your friends who's
not very nice person and after they
start meditating with you let's see
how's the water in your mind the house
your heartbeat
how's your breathing let's check is
there any difference between the state
of your mind and your heart beat and
your breathing when these two friends
are around you
now a different scene you are in your
retreat cabin this evening or this
afternoon and you're alone in your room
and you're not meditating but you're
just relaxing sitting maybe enjoying the
nature here the sky at sunset for
example it's very beautiful here and
you're just sitting and looking out the
window
at the sunset and how does your mind
water feel how's the breathing how's the
heartbeat
and last part please think about all the
things you have to do next week when you
come home things that have been waiting
for you
responsibilities bills
tasks for your job things you have to do
for your work try to think of some of
them and see what it does to your
heartbeat your breathing and the peace
of your mind the water of your mind
then please come back to morning mined
in Diamond Mountain come back to this
date of mine you had when we started the
meditation quiet peaceful
three long exhales
and then slowly open your eyes and take
a stretch drink something okay drink
something you guys have a microphone
ready anybody want to talk about how did
your mind change three kinds of mind one
is morning at Diamond Mountain and one
is sitting with a friend who's a good
person and one is sitting with a friend
who's not a very nice person
and how did your breath change how did
your heartbeat change how did the water
in your mind change anybody want to talk
about it
no need Bokke or or bokuto boko or
bokuto
you couldn't find one you're a lucky
person okay so you don't need love em
yeah yeah that's fine yeah yeah yeah
okay cool anybody else
yeah cool okay hustle Nicole
good yeah good yeah again yeah good
anybody else pocket change
[Music]
good
Oh
[Music]
okay poke achieve
Oh
okay behind behind very patient
[Music]
cool okay anyone else cheek me is that
your friend
okay one more
oh no yeah okay no Ben
[Music]
[Laughter]
he sells Audi's ok ok ok cool
Pasha Pavan
goodwife you thinking about
[Music]
so those are we're gonna go back to the
lung room okay we're gonna start because
we've been going kind of slow which is
what geshe-la does and there are six
triggers for cliche there are six
triggers for negative thoughts and we
did one of them the other day and that's
where you think about you get in the
presence of someone who's causing you
trouble okay so in Tibetan that's called
mikvah presence of the object so the
thing that you have an addiction for
someone's comes in the room eating a
doughnut and geshe-la
desire clashes starts to get strong or
someone comes in the room especially if
you didn't expect them and you had
trouble with them in the past and the
presence of the object whether it's a
doughnut or someone you had a fight with
before it starts to put you off balance
right and those of you who studied ACI
sorry DCI level 10 this is the
preliminary to getting upset and getting
upset is the preliminary to anger and
anger is the preliminary
or resentment you know holding it for
weeks or months or years there's a big
joke a nun I went to a talk by a
Buddhist nun and she said something
cause she said uh you know the
ex-boyfriend who called you stupid he
forgot about it the next day but you
still remember 20 years later you still
hold it you still remember these fights
you had with people so the first trick
there's six triggers for clay sure there
are six triggers and we're going through
them man manda very slow first trigger
the person
yeah the object the person or the donut
comes in the room okay and then the
breath starts to speed up the heart
starts to speed up and the morning
diamond mountain piece for mine water
starts to get choppy okay and so those
are preliminary to getting so it goes
like that
off balance first you get off balance
then you get upset upset you still
didn't say anything yet angry you say
something and then resentment you hold
it for weeks or months okay after that
there's four steps - clay sure okay
most Glacius so what we learned the
other day is one approach for beginners
lower school because it doesn't work
over here just work sometimes try to
avoid the person or try to avoid donors
you know ask your friends not to bring
doughnuts in the room okay and it's not
a very good method but it's better than
nothing and find out the address of your
ex-husband ex-wife and never go to that
city make sure you follow their travel
plans
and never meet them you know okay and
it's not easy all right
and it doesn't work very well karma will
bring them to you somehow or they're
your friend we'll start talking about
them and your heartbeats speech speeds
up and your breasts pizza okay so that's
called object factor one of the six
triggers for achalasia okay second
trigger we had today is bad france we
call dick jokes a dick joke say judo
dicto judo Dopey's friend okay
dick means bad bad karma friend and then
cheedo means a good karma friend and
generally shadow if you hang out with
them I was thinking about Rob Russ
injure I don't think he's here so I can
talk about him he's so nice
and he's so steady and he's so humble
and he's so sweet
and he works so hard for all of us he
does all the accounting for a couple of
projects and perfectly and so when
you're around him your water stays calm
right called Chi dog dumb ofin and then
dick dog means that I don't know you
around someone who's nervous or gets
irritated easily or says bad things to
people and then it infects you it
affects your behavior it speeds up your
heart normally speeds up your breath
okay so there's a tradition lower school
okay lower school try to not hang out
with those bad friends very often try to
hang out more with the Rob recen jurists
okay and I don't know write a couple
people said bad friends not really a
friend you know like I had trouble
thinking about a friend who's bad
because when a friend is bad if you
don't want to be a friend
to be honest we all have bad friends it
seems like I don't know why we stay
around them but we do and so in the
Dharma in the Lum room
be careful with your choice of friends
and try to spend more hours with the
nice friends and then their habits their
behavior will rub off on you it will
infect you and try to reduce the time
you spend with people who are angry
people or jealous people okay because no
matter how hard you try they will affect
you they will affect you you will start
to act like them okay that's the second
one okay first one object you know lower
school avoid that trigger you know
geshe-la should never go to Dunkin
Donuts at all or Tim Horton okay just I
should just avoid it forever and I try
you know not real hard but that is bad
thing in the airport it's called
Cinnabon and I think they have a fan and
they send the smell of the Cinnabon
throughout the airport and it's really
hard to not smell it
I guess that's their plan so the second
thing is who do you associate with okay
who do you associate with what was the
third one is called Lindsey said Dunsey
Dinsey it's a good word for word to
learn do you know it dingy means too
busy overstimulated okay too much to do
too much coffee too many plans too many
thoughts it's very famous word it's
called dingy and dark yunduo Nagi cozy
didn't
okay and it just means a breeding ground
for clay chef is a busy mine
okay if and they and the Internet is
like 99% Dinsey okay and it's it's
unfortunate I mean it's a good karma in
our life like it's revolutionizing
Dharma teaching right you can or yoga
you can get a hundred classes on YouTube
thousand classes on YouTube for free and
that's wonderful that's a great thing
but uh but it also keeps your mind
really busy and scattered maybe Dungey
is scattered mine in English it means
you're just thinking about too many
things and that's a good place clashes
like to grow there
it's like fertilizer foreclosures okay
if you get too busy your heartbeat
speeds up your breath speeds up you feel
like you're running a race right you
know and that's a good place for clashes
to grow okay so we've covered three
triggers okay the object comes in the
room you have friends who influence you
and then your mind is too scattered and
then it's more likely that you will get
angry or you will have jealousy or
desire okay so part of the idea of
diamond mountain is to temporarily right
help you with those three triggers you
know you're in a cabin your ex-wife
probably won't come then you're trying
to be around good people here you know
people are not going to come out here if
they're not nice people usually and then
third one is you know you're cut down
you're not so busy right while you're
here and unless there's a teacher
training or something okay all right so
we've discussed three triggers now I'd
like to go to the
I'd like to go to the alarm room and
start start reading more in lung room
watch the three triggers okay this is
lower school it doesn't always work okay
we didn't get to higher school it's the
higher schoolers first trigger okay we
didn't get to it yet okay
all right here we go